Gerald P. Mace Collection of Textile Industry Photographs 6663 P
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Gerald P. Mace Collection of Textile Industry Photographs
1959
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Gerald P. Mace
6663 P
1 folders
1 file folder
Photographs.
Photos taken of the machine shop at the Merrimack Manufacturing Company.
10065753
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
R. Miles, October 13, 2017
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, November 16, 2017
Scope and Contents
Originally housed in envelope labelled "Photos of Machine Shop - Merrimack Manufacturing Co. - For Jim Mace in return for many kindnesses - W.G. Ogden, Jr., Experimental Machine Work, Winter St., R.F.D., South Lincoln, Mass."
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6780: Merrimack Manufacturing Records
Blacksmithing; Brooms and brushes; Electric welding; Gear-cutting machines; Industrial equipment; Lathes; Machine shops; Machine-tools; Milling machinery; Planing-machines; Press; Pulleys; Shears (Machine-tools); Spindles (Textile machinery); Textile industry--England; Textile machinery; Tools; Woodworking machinery; Wrenches; Industries--Fitchburg (Mass.); Industries--Worcester (Mass.); Dexter (Me.); Putnam (Conn.); Fitchburg Machine Works.; Gay, Silver & Company.; Ira Gay and Company.; Merrimack Manufacturing Company.; Rock River Woolen Mills (Janesville, Wis.); Saws; Silver & Gay's Machine Shop (North Chelmsford, Mass.); Silver, Gay & Company (North Chelmsford, Mass.)
10065753
- Merrimack Manufacturing Company Machinery, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 1: Staple Vice/Typical, main machine shop - 360-26, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Merrimack Manufacturing Co., 1822- 1959, Photograph taken ca. 1959.
    Format: black and white photograph.
  - Item 2: #8092 Slabbing Machine, 1855 - 361-3, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gay, Silver & Co. founded in 1832 by Ira Gay of Dunstable, N.H. - Aug 1836-1859 with the above style [Ira Gay & Co., 1832-1836 (August)]. May 22, 1834 - see South Midd'x Registry of Deeds, Lincoln Drake to Ira Gay, Record book 332, pp. 130-132. Photograph taken ca. 1959.
  - Item 3: #8092 Slabbing Machine, 1855 - 361-5, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gay, Silver & Company was called North Chelmsford Machine Co. from 1898 until February 1905. Photograph taken ca. 1959.
  - Item 4: #8004 Combination Double Shear and Punch- 360-35, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Rock River, 1917. Photograph taken ca. 1959.
  - Item 5: #8071 MM Co. #16 - 361-8, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Possibly by Gay, Silver & Company before 1870. The step pulley is made of wood. Photograph taken ca. 1959.
  - Item 6: #8098 Slotting Machine, No. 3 Vertical, 1880, 360-20, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Merrimack Manufacturing Co. #31. Patented March 14, 1871 by Salmon W. Putnam, Jr. Photograph taken ca. 1959.
  - Item 7: #8092 Slabbing Machine, 1855 - 361-2, 1959; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    13 July 1959. Photograph by Oswald Cammann, MIT, for W. G. Ogden, Jr.
  - Item 7: #8060 Slabbing Machine, Planer Type, 1870, (22x11x5'6") - 360-29, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Silver & Gay Company, North Chelmsford, Mass., 1860-1897 with the above style, Assessor's Records town of Chelmsford. Merrimack Manufacturing Co. #22 Basement. Photograph taken ca. 1959.
  - Item 9: 600 lb. Hammer (1925) in background, and 150 lb. Beaudry Hammer (1928) - 360-33, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Blacksmith & Welding Shop, Merrimack Manufacturing Co Photograph taken ca. 1959.
  - Item 10: Machine Shop, Merrimack Manufacturing Co. - 360-15, 1959; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    July 1959.
  - Item 11: Blacksmith and Welding Shop, Forges, from main entrance - 360-32, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Photograph taken ca. 1959.
  - Item 12: #8092 Slabbing Machine, Planer Type, 1855 - 360-36, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gay, Silver & Company, North Chelmsford, Mass., authority of W. G. Ogden, Jr., August 1836-1859. Merrimack Manufacturing Co. #23. Photograph taken ca. 1959.
  - Item 13: #8092 Slabbing Machine, 1855 - 361-4, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gay, Silver & Company, August 1836- 1859. Closed business in 1924 as North Chelmsford Machine & Supply Co., February 1905-1924. Photograph taken ca. 1959.
  - Item 14: #8072 Head end/with nameplate - 361-7, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Wood, Light & Co., Worcester, 1875. Double Head, engine lathe 20" swing x 21' O.A. Merrimack Manufacturing Co. #2. Photograph taken ca. 1959.
  - Item 15: #8073 Engine Lathe 20" swing x 13' O.A. - 360-25, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Putnam Machine Works, 1910. Photograph taken ca. 1959.
  - Item 16: #8060 Slabbing Machine 1870 - 360-31, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Silver & Gay Company, 1860-1897. Photograph taken ca. 1959.
  - Item 17: #8073 Engine Lathe 20" swing x 13' O.A. - 360-24, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 18: #8282 Hand or Burning Down Lathe 1870 - 360-14, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    In Brush Shop, 2nd floor. Photograph taken ca. 1959.
  - Item 19: #8060 Slabbing Machine 1870 - 360-30, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 20: #8102 High-Speed, Draw Cut Hacksaw - 360-21, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Racine 1916. Photograph taken ca. 1959.
  - Item 21: View from Tool Crib - 360-15, 1959; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Machine Shop, Merrimack Manufacturing Co. July 1959.
  - Item 22: #8127 Full Auto Gear Cutting Mach. #6" - 360-9, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Brainard Milling Machine Co., 1910. Merrimack Manufacturing Co. #33. Photograph taken ca. 1959.
  - Item 23: #8072 end number two- 361-6, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Wood, Light & Co. Worcester, 1875. Double Head, Engine Lathe 20" swing x 21' O.A. - Merrimack Manufacturing Co. #2. Photograph taken ca. 1959.
  - Item 24: #8223 Wood Working Lathe 24" x 7'-6" 11'-0" O.A. - 361-12, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Old Chain Feed Lathe, converted to Tin Covering Machine, 1875. Possibly Gay, Silver & Co. Photograph taken ca. 1959.
  - Item 25: #8071 listed as a Flather 1900, but this is certainly no Flather - 361-9, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    This is possibly and Engine Lathe by Gay, Silver & Co., the legs bear a strong resemblance to those on the Slabber. The style of this lathe is definitely before 1870. Merrimack Manufacturing Co #16. Photograph taken ca. 1959.
  - Item 26: #8063 Straightening Press, 1900/Left corner of photograph and #8051 J. Neal & Co. 1870 - 72" swing x 18'-0" O.A. - 360-28, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 27: #8093 Planing Machine 48" x 48" x 10' - 2 heads - 360-23, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    The Powell Planer Co., Worcester, 1880. Photograph taken ca. 1959.
  - Item 28: #8223 Wood Working Lathe 24" x 7'-6" 11'-0" O.A. - 361-11, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 29: #8224 Wood Working Lathe 16" x 6'-0" 9'-0" O.A. - 361-10, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    1870. Photograph taken ca. 1959. B35
  - Item 30: #8051 J. Neal & Co. 1870 72" swing x 18'-0" O.A. - 360-27, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Note Raising Blocks and Square Tailstock spindle. Photograph taken ca. 1959.
  - Item 31: Forged Tools for Shaper and Slotter - 360-12, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 32: #8107 Vertical Drill No. 799, 1860 - 360-22, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Smith & Coventry, Manchester, England, Merrimack Manufacturing Co. #51. Photograph taken ca. 1959.
  - Item 33: #8094 Traverse Head Shaper - 360-18, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Fitchburg Machine Works No. 2, 1885. Photograph taken ca. 1959.
  - Item 34: Rack of Forged Tools/Tool crib - 360-13, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 35: #8222 Wood Working Lathe 24" x 6'-6" 10'-0" O.A. - 361-13, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Fay & Scott, Builders, Dexter, Maine, 1890. Note swiveling headstock. Photograph taken ca. 1959.
  - Item 36: #8282 Hand or Burning Down Lathe 1870 - 361-15, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    In Brush Shop 2nd floor. Photograph taken ca. 1959.
  - Item 37: #8121 Straightening Press, Screw Type - 1900 - 360-19, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 38: #8094 Traverse Head Shaper - 360-17, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 39: Forged Lathe Dogs & Work Drivers - 360-11, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 40: Straight Tail Lathe Dogs - 360-14, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Forged Tap and Reamer Wrenches. Photograph taken ca. 1959.